Guide to the Donald E. Knuth papers SC0097
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Donald E. Knuth papers
1962-2018
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
SC0097
Archival Resource Key
Previous Archival Resource Key
39.75 Linear Feet
4.3 gigabyte(s) email files
Papers reflect his work in the study and teaching of computer programming, computer systems for publishing, and mathematics. Included are correspondence, notes, manuscripts, computer printouts, logbooks, proofs, and galleys pertaining to the computer systems TeX, METAFONT, and Computer Modern; and to his books THE ART OF COMPUTER PROGRAMMING, COMPUTERS & TYPESETTING, CONCRETE MATHEMATICS, THE STANFORD GRAPHBASE, DIGITAL TYPOGRAPHY, SELECTED PAPERS ON ANALYSIS OF ALGORITHMS, MMIXWARE: A RISC COMPUTER FOR THE THIRD MILLENNIUM, and THINGS A COMPUTER SCIENTIST RARELY TALKS ABOUT.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Donald Knuth, 1972, 1980, 1983, 1989, 1996, 1998, 2001, 2014, 2015, 2019.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
The full text version of the email contained in this collection is available in the Field Reading Room; a redacted version, displaying correspondents and extracted entities (personal and corporate names and locations) from Knuth's email have been published in Stanford's online discovery module: http://epadd.stanford.edu/epadd/collections. 515 messages have been entirely restricted from both the discovery module and the full text version available in the reading room according to federal and state guidelines, and Stanford Libraries policy, for up to 80 years. These messages may contain financial, medical, legal, and other sensitive information. They will be made available in 2099.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in three series and subsequent accessions: Series 1. The Art of Computer Programming; Series 2. Computers and Typesetting; Series 3. Concrete Mathematics.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Donald Ervin Knuth's work established the analysis of algorithms as an academic field. He contributed to the development of the rigorous analysis of the computational complexity of algorithms and systematized formal mathematical techniques for it. In the process he also popularized the asymptotic notation.
In addition to fundamental contributions in several branches of theoretical computer science, Knuth is the creator of the TeX computer typesetting system, the related METAFONT font definition language and rendering system, and the Computer Modern family of typefaces.
As a writer and scholar, Knuth created the WEB/CWEB computer programming systems designed to encourage and facilitate literate programming, and designed the MIX/MMIX instruction set architectures.
Professor of computer science at Stanford University from 1968-1992, Knuth was born in January 10, 1938 in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. He received a B.S. from Case Institute of Technology in 1960 and a Ph.D. from the California Institute of Technology in 1963. That same year he began to work on The Art of Computer Programming. He had initially accepted a commission to write a book on compilers which would later become the multi-volume The Art of Computer Programming. Originally planned to be a single book, and then planned as a six- and then seven-volume series. In 1968, he published the first volume.
After producing the third volume of his series in 1976, he expressed such frustration with the nascent state of the then newly developed electronic publishing tools (especially those that provided input to phototypesetters) that he took time out to work on typesetting and created the TeX and METAFONT tools. At the TUG 2010 Conference, Knuth announced an XML-based successor to TeX, titled "iTeX", which would support features such as arbitrarily scaled irrational units, 3D printing, animation, and stereographic sound.
Knuth has won numerous awards for his work, including:
First ACM Grace Murray Hopper Award, 1971 Turing Award, 1974 National Medal of Science, 1979 Franklin Medal, 1988 John von Neumann Medal, 1995 Harvey Prize from the Technion, 1995 Kyoto Prize, 1996 Katayanagi Prize, 2010 BBVA Foundation Frontiers of Knowledge Award, 2010 Stanford University School of Engineering Hero Award, 2011
He was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1975. In 1992, he became an associate of the French Academy of Sciences. Also that year, he retired from regular research and teaching at Stanford University in order to finish The Art of Computer Programming. In 2003, he was elected as a foreign member of the Royal Society. Knuth was elected as a Fellow (first class of Fellows) of the Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics in 2009 for his outstanding contributions to mathematics. He is also a member of the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters.
On June 24, 1961 he married Nancy June Carter (b. July 15, 1939). They have two children: John Martin (b. July 21, 1965) and Jennifer Sierra (b. December 12, 1966).
Description of the Collection
Papers reflect his work in the study and teaching of computer programming, computer systems for publishing, and mathematics. Included are correspondence, notes, manuscripts, computer printouts, logbooks, proofs, and galleys pertaining to the computer systems TeX, METAFONT, and Computer Modern; and to his books THE ART OF COMPUTER PROGRAMMING, COMPUTERS & TYPESETTING, CONCRETE MATHEMATICS, THE STANFORD GRAPHBASE, DIGITAL TYPOGRAPHY, SELECTED PAPERS ON ANALYSIS OF ALGORITHMS, MMIXWARE: A RISC COMPUTER FOR THE THIRD MILLENNIUM, and THINGS A COMPUTER SCIENTIST RARELY TALKS ABOUT.
Computer programs.; Computer science.; Computer scientists.; TeX (Computer system).; College teachers.; METAFONT (Computer system).; Computerized typesetting.
- The Art of Computer Programming, Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Hand-written notes on The Art of Computer Programming, computer print-outs that were prepared for this book, various stages of the second edition of volume 2 of the book, 1980 revisions of the book, and the TeX form of the book. Also included is the correspondence received on the book, and correspondence between Knuth and his editor, Marion Howe.
  The Art of Computer Programming describes the body of scientific knowledge on the programming of digital computers. The second edition led to Dr. Knuth's development of METAFONT, his computer design typeface system allowing subtle changes in alphabet design, and his page-formatting system, TeX; both systems are intended for the creation of beautiful books by the hand of the original author/printer.
  Notes on the second edition of Volume 2, by Donald Knuth, July 30, 1980:
  I began to revise the first edition in November 1974, just after finishing revisions for the second printing of Volume 3. Worked steadily until October 1975, preparing hundreds of hand-written inserts. The intent was to preserve the existing page numbering. Marion Howe at Addison-Wesley unscrambled my manuscript using scissors, tape, etc. During 1976, Addison-Wesley found that the number of changes necessitated a complete resetting of the book. Cost of Monotype had skyrocketed; tried to match fonts on Linotron 505, no luck. I discussed the problem with Addison-Wesley chairman (Cummings) during a visit to Boston; decision was made to prepare new fonts for Linotron 505 by photographing the old ones. First results of this were awful; they tried to tune things up. Finally in the spring of 1977, I decided to work on typography myself, and I told them to stop trying as their method was not going to work. During the rest of 1977, I developed TeX and proto-METAFONT; was ready to compose Volume 2 in spring of 1978. I mostly worked on METAFONT and refinements to TeX during 1979, then returned to Volume 2 in 1980, when I made further technical revisions during April-June to incorporate the research results accumulated since 1975.
  I saved the following things for Archives: A. Original manuscript, as unscrambled by Marion Howe. B. Galley proofs from Universities Press, Belfast, showing why I got into typesetting. C. Galley proofs I made while recomposing the book in 1978. D. TeX form of Chapter 3 at the time I sent Addison-Wesley the first results of my work (June 1978). E. Marion Howe's comments on my initial try at Chapter 3. F. The state of the entire book as of the end of 1978: Chapter 3 revised, and Chapter 4 in its initial form. This copy also shows markings made by Marion Howe, and changes I made during 1980 (this was my source document for the final revision in 1980). G. The state of the entire book after 1980 revision but before proofreading by Aspvall and Liang, and before the final revision of the Computer Modern fonts. H. The state of the book just before final camera-ready copy made, showing last-minute refinements and the index. I. TeX form of the book as printed.
  Boxes 31-36: Subsequent editions of Volumes 1, 2 and 3
  Notes, by Donald Knuth, August 25, 1988
  From February 1995 to February 1998, my major project was to produce new editions of the existing volumes of The Art of Computer Programming: Volume 1 (3rd edition), Volume 2 (3rd edition), and Volume 3 (2nd edition). These were the first new editions of Volumes 1 and 3 since 1975, and the first new edition of Volume 2 since 1981. My work on typesetting, and other projects such as Concrete Mathematics, 3:16 Bible Texts Illuminated, and The Stanford GraphBase, had occupied nearly all of my time since 1977; now I could best return to The Art of Computer Programming by applying the typesetting software I had constructed to the main task that had motivated it from the beginning.
  The first major use of TeX had been to produce the second edition of Volume 2 in 1981. My secretary, Phyllis Winkler, then put the texts of Volumes 1 and 3 into the same form; but I never had had time to use the results of her work, because the international use of TeX had become so great that I knew I would have to completely revise that system. Thus in 1995 all I had "online" was a set of approximations to Volumes 1, 2, and 3, expressed in an old version of the TeX language that had become obsolete in 1982.
  I also had received many hundreds of letters from readers, and had made significant amendments to the text; I began to put those changes into electronic form, as a 350-page list of errata to the old editions. Silvio Levy volunteered to convert the old TeX files to modern TeX form, and to incorporate all of the new errata, while carefully proofreading everything; he began this work in 1996, while I was still gather the errata together.
  Finally in January of 1997, my errata lists were complete, and Silvio had also finished preparing the new electronic version of Volume 1. I began on January 11 to prepare the final version of that volume, and I had the first ten pages done on January 31.
  Meanwhile another volunteer, Jeffrey Oldham, had begun to convert all of the illustrations to electronic form in the METAPOST language – a major undertaking involving more than 600 illustrations, many of which were quite complex. While I was working on Volume 1, Levy and Oldham continued to prepare the text and illustrations for Volumes 2 and 3.
  I soon found that the existence of these documents in electronic form changed everything: The temptation to make small improvements (once prohibitively expensive but now easy) became irresistible. Therefore I soon found that I wanted to make dozens of improvements to every page. Fortunately the typographical tools now available made it possible for me to do this with reasonable speed, and I completed Volume 1 at 4am on April 21.
  Volume 2 was more of the same; I began it on April 29 and finished on September 3 (this time at 5:30 am). Work on Volume 3 began on September 16 – coincidentally the day my first grandchild was born! -- and consumed most of my energy until 4:30 am on February 27, 1998. The completed volumes totaled 670 +776 + 794 = 2240 pages.
  In these boxes I have placed the main things that seem to be worth archiving:
  0a. Xerox of the notebook entries I made while doing the work. 0b. Copies of email correspondence with Silvio Levy, 1995-1998. 1a. Volume 1 illustration proofs, showing the figures as received from Jeffrey Oldham. Handwritten corrections show most of the changes that I incorporated into the master files as I polished the book. 1b. Volume 1 first proofs: Pages formatted as received from Levy, with markings to show changes that I made while proofreading. (Most of the corrections are in green ink; red ink shows later changes made after the "green" ones were already corrected. This saved paper!) When I made extensive amendments, my first pencil drafts are often interfiled; but the drafts of shorter amendments were not saved. 1c. Volume 1 after I had completed one pass over the entire book. I laserprinted just this one copy and had it velo-bound, for use in preparing the index; then I circled items that needed to be indexed. 1d. Volume 1 index proofs: An inverted index of the old edition (used to cross-check that my new indexing hadn't forgotten anything), followed by the first proof of the new index. 2a, 2b, 2c, 2d. Same as above, but for Volume 2. 3a, 3b, 3c, 3d. Same as above, but for Volume 3.
  - Dedication and Introduction to The Art of Computer Programming (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, changes to the first edition (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 1 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 2 (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 3 (Box 1, Folder 13 - 15)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 4 outline, notes (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 4 (Box 1, Folder 17 - 31)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 4 and 5 brief drafts (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 5 (Box 1, Folder 33 - 45)
  - Sorting techniques (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 5, p. 1-40 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Chapter 6 (Box 1, Folder 48 - 55)
  - Correspondence and notes on chapter 7 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Chapter 9 and information on scanner (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - p. 11-138 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - p. 139-221 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - p. 222-272 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - p. 410-445 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - p. 610-634 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - A3 - A23 Algorithm (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Algorithm, p. 507, 508, 540 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Algorithm for inverse pennutation (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The analysis of radix exchange (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Componological problem in group theory (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chapter organization (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Combinational searching (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Distribution for cascade (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Evaluation of polynomials (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Example, the boy and the apple tree (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Factor method tree (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Finite state language (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Formulas and readings (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Generalized zero-one principle (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - A good scrambling function for hardware (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Historical names and places (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Historical roles (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Index and glossary (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Index entries (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Index material (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Information on integers (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Information on quick sort (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Introduction to the book (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - latin square (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Maclaren's method/algorithm (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - MIX: Math Department subroutine 10/8/62 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Names list (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Non-isomorphic solutions to "queens" problem (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Notes for class (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Optimal search tree (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Optinn.nn sorting (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Organizational outline for the book (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Organization of book (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Page conunentaries (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Pagination changes (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Permutations of a finite multi-set (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Polynomials (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Polynomial division (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - The power tree (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Preface and index (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Preparing for polyphase merge (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Radix system (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Random mnnbers sorting (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Recurring series mod m (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - References (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Run-distribution alternating directions (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - SIAM Review 9 / 1967 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Sorting (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Sorting information (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - statistical study of published algorithurns (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Subroutines p. 1-36, caltech, Fall 1963 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Summary for 1/29-30/72 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Tables I (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Tables II (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Tablet with book organization (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Theory and techniques for design of electronic digital computer (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - 38 exercises (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Three tran algorithm (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Traffic signal problem (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Unification problem (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Utility arithmetic subroutines (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Computer print-outs on experiments with sort routines, algorithms, cascade merge programs, Morteson table, source listing (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 1-49 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 69-135 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 136-191 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 192-236 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 237-316 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 317-380 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 381-435 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 436-501 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript of The Art of Computer Programming, p. 502-545 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 546-595 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 596-635 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 636-683 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 685-734 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 735-776 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 777-808 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 809-843 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 844-851 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, p. 7-30 miscellaneous information (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Art of Computer Programming, Volume II, Galley proofs from universities press (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chapter 3 and introduction (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chapter 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 3 continued (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chapter 4 (Box 6, Folder 5-10)
  - Answers to exercises, section 3, section 4 (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
  - TeX form of chapter 3 (Box 7)
  - Marion Howe's comments on the state of the book, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 1-36 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 37-111 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 112-175 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 176-246 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 247-298 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 299-309 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 310-386 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 387-485 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 486-494 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 495-540 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - State of the book, 1978, p. 541-632 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - State of the book, 1980 revisions, p. 1-113 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - State of the book, 1980 revisions, p. 114-177 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - State of the book, 1980 revisions, p. 178-249 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - State of the book, 1980 revisions, p. 250-312 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - State of the book, 1980 revisions, p. 313-398 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - State of the book, 1980 revisions, p. 399-466 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Proofs for the 3rd edition of Volumes 1 and 2 and for the 2nd edition of Volume 3
    - Notebook entries (photocopies) (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - E-mail with Silvio Levy 1995 Aug. - 1996 Feb. (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - E-mail with Silvio Levy 1996 Mar. - July (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - E-mail with Silvio Levy 1996 Aug. - 1997 Mar. (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - E-mail with Silvio Levy 1997 May - 1998 Jan. (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Volume 1 illustration proofs (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Volume 1 Proofs: Preface - p. 99 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Volume 1 Proofs: pp. 100-199 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Volume 1 Proofs: pp. 200-299 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Volume 1 Proofs: pp. 300-399 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Volume 1 Proofs: pp. 400-499 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Volume 1 Proofs: pp. 500-624 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Volume 1 Bound Proof (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Volume 1 Index Proofs (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Volume 2 illustration proofs (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Volume 2 Proofs: Preface - p. 99 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Volume 2 Proofs: pp. 100-300 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Volume 2 Proofs: pp. 301-500 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Volume 2 Proofs: pp. 501 - end (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Volume 2 Bound Proof (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Volume 2 Index Proofs (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Volume 3 illustration proofs (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Preface and section 5.2 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Section 5.2.1 - 5.2.3 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Section 5.2.4 - 5.3.3 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Section 5.3.4 - 5.4.4 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Section 5.4.5 - 6.2.1 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Section 6.2.2 - 6.3 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Volume 3 Proofs: Section 6.4 - end (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Volume 3 Index Proofs (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Volume 3 Chapter 5 Bound Proof (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Volume 3 Chapter 6 Bound Proof (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - p. 467-505 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - p. 506-546 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - p. 601-647 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Appendices (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - p. v-99 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - p. 100-199 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - p. 200-299 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - p. 300-399 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - p. 400-499 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - p. 500-599 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - p. 600-688 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - TeX form of the book (Box 11, Folder 1-22)
- Computers and Typesetting, Series 2
  This set of 14 boxes contains materials from nine years of work on computer systems for publishing at stanford. 'The main results of this work have been published in five volumes entitled Computers & Typesetting, Volumes A--E (Reading, Mass.: Addison Wesley, 1986).
  The research introduced three major computer systems:
  1) TeX, a system for typesetting
  2) METAFONT, a system for typeface design
  3) Computer Modern, a family of typefaces
  Another important byproduct was the WEB system for structured documentation of computer programs.
  Included are the original manuscripts, revised drafts, logbooks, commentary from other experts, research files, and correspondence pertaining to three major computer systems: TeX, a system for typesetting, METAFONT, a system for typeface design, and Computer Modern, a family of typefaces. Also included are keepsakes and specimens of early use of these systems.